window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Algorithms - Algorithms — Slot 12 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Algorithms — Slot 12",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Selection sort algorithm design technique is an example of <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Divide-and-conquer</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Dynamic Programming</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49537/isro2007-55\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider a job scheduling problem with 4 jobs \\(J_1, J_2, J_3\\) and \\(J_4\\) with corresponding deadlines: \\((d_1, d_2, d_3, d_4) = (4, 2, 4, 2)\\). Which of the following is not a feasible schedule without violating any job schedule? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(J_2, J_4, J_1, J_3\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(J_4, J_1, J_2, J_3\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(J_4, J_2, J_1, J_3\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(J_4, J_2, J_3, J_1\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(J_4, J_1, J_2, J_3\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49483/isro2007-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider n jobs \\(J_1, J_2 \\dots J_n\\) such that job \\(J_i\\) has execution time \\(t_i\\) and a non-negative integer weight \\(w_i\\). The weighted mean completion time of the jobs is defined to be \\(\\frac{\\sum_{i=1}^{n}w_iT_i}{\\sum_{i=1}^{n}w_i}\\), where \\(T_i\\) is the completion time of job \\(J_i\\). Assuming that there is only one processor available, in what order must the jobs be executed in order to minimize the weighted mean completion time of the jobs? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Non-decreasing order of \\(t_i\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Non-increasing order of \\(w_i\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Non-increasing order of \\(w_it_i\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Non-increasing order of \\(w_i/t_i\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Non-increasing order of \\(w_i/t_i\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3459/gate2007-it-26\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>What is the largest integer m such that every simple connected graph with n vertices and n edges contains at least m different spanning trees ? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3458/gate2007-it-25\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>A depth-first search is performed on a directed acyclic graph. Let d[u] denote the time at which vertex u is visited for the first time and f[u] the time at which the DFS call to the vertex u terminates. Which of the following statements is always TRUE for all edges (u, v) in the graph ? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>d[u] &lt; d[v]</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>d[u] &lt; f[v]</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>f[u] &lt; f[v]</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>f[u] &gt; f[v]</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>f[u] &gt; f[v]</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3457/gate2007-it-24\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Exponentiation is a heavily used operation in public key cryptography. Which of the following options is the tightest upper bound on the number of multiplications required to compute \\(b^n \\bmod{m}, 0 \\leq b, n \\leq m\\) ? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(\\sqrt n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O\\Biggl (\\frac{n}{\\log n} \\Biggr )\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(\\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3450/gate2007-it-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider a weighted, undirected graph with positive edge weights and let \\(uv\\) be an edge in the graph. It is known that the shortest path from the source vertex \\(s\\) to \\(u\\) has weight 53 and the shortest path from \\(s\\) to \\(v\\) has weight 65. Which one of the following statements is always TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Weight \\((u,v) \\leq 12\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Weight (u,v) = 12</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Weight \\((u,v) \\geq 12\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Weight (u,v) &gt; 12</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Weight \\((u,v) \\geq 12\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3434/gate2007-it-3-ugcnet-june2012-iii-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that a robot is placed on the Cartesian plane. At each step it is allowed to move either one unit up or one unit right, i.e., if it is at (i,j) then it can move to either (i+1,j) or (i,j+1).  <br> <br> Suppose that the robot is not allowed to traverse the line segment from (4,4) to\n(5,4). With this constraint, how many distinct paths are there for the robot to\nreach (10,10) starting from (0,0)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(2^{9}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{19}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{pmatrix} 8\\\\ 4 \\end{pmatrix}*\\begin{pmatrix} 11\\\\ 5 \\end{pmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{pmatrix} 20\\\\ 10 \\end{pmatrix}-\\begin{pmatrix} 8\\\\ 4 \\end{pmatrix}*\\begin{pmatrix} 11\\\\ 5 \\end{pmatrix}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{pmatrix} 20\\\\ 10 \\end{pmatrix}-\\begin{pmatrix} 8\\\\ 4 \\end{pmatrix}*\\begin{pmatrix} 11\\\\ 5 \\end{pmatrix}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43509/gate2007-85#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that a robot is placed on the Cartesian plane. At each step it is allowed to move either one unit up or one unit right, i.e., if it is at (i,j) then it can move to either (i+1,j) or (i,j+1).  <br> <br> How many distinct paths are there for the robot to reach the point (10,10)\nstarting from the initial position (0,0)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{pmatrix} 20\\\\ 10 \\end{pmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{20}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{pmatrix} 20\\\\ 10 \\end{pmatrix}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1275/gate2007-84#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Suppose the letters a, b, c, d, e, f have probabilities 1/2, 1/4, 1/8, 1/16, 1/32, 1/32 respectively.  <br><br>What is the average length of  the Huffman code for the letters a,b,c,d,e,f? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2.1875</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2.25</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1.9375</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>1.9375</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43513/gate2007-77#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Suppose the letters a, b, c, d, e, f have probabilities 1/2, 1/4, 1/8, 1/16, 1/32, 1/32 respectively. <br><br>Which of the following is the Huffman code for the letter a, b, c, d, e, f? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0, 10, 110, 1110, 11110, 11111</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>11, 10, 011, 010, 001, 000</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>11, 10, 01, 001, 0001, 0000</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>110, 100, 010, 000, 001, 111</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>0, 10, 110, 1110, 11110, 11111</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1271/gate2007-76#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following C code segment:<pre><code> int IsPrime(n)\n{\n  int i,n;\n  for(i=2;i&lt;=sqrt(n);i++)\n     if(n%i == 0)\n      {printf(\"Not Primen\"); return 0;}\n  return 1;\n} </code></pre>\nLet T(n)denote the number of times the for loop is executed by the program on\ninput n. Which of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=O(\\sqrt{n}) \\; and \\; T(n)=\\Omega (\\sqrt{n})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=O(n)  \\; and \\;  T(n)=\\Omega (\\sqrt{n})\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=O(\\sqrt{n})  \\; and \\;  T(n)=\\Omega (1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=O(\\sqrt{n})  \\; and \\;  T(n)=\\Omega (1)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1249/gate2007-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Let w be the minimum weight among all edge weights in an undirected connected\ngraph. Let e be a specific edge of weight w . Which of the following is FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>There is a minimum spanning tree containing e.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If e is not in a minimum spanning tree T, then in the cycle formed by adding\ne to T, all edges have the same weight.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Every minimum spanning tree has an edge of weight w .</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>e is present in every minimum spanning tree.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>e is present in every minimum spanning tree.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1247/gate2007-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>What is the Asymptotic Notation of the following recursive function:<pre><code> int DoSomething (int n) \n{\n  if (n &lt;= 2)\n    return 1;\n  else \n    return (DoSomething (floor(sqrt(n))) + n);\n}</code></pre> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n log_{2} n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (log_{2} n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (log_{2} log_{2}n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (log_{2} log_{2}n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1243/gate2007-45#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>In the following C function, let n\\(\\geq\\)m.<pre><code>int gcd(n,m)\n{\n  if (n%m ==0) return m;  \n  n = n%m;\n  return gcd(m,n);\n}</code></pre>\nHow many recursive calls are made by this function? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Omega (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (log logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\sqrt{n})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (logn)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1242/gate2007-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
